Frederick Loewe Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Frederick Loewe Collection 1923-1988 (bulk 1945-1975)
ML31.L58
Frederick Loewe, 1901-1988
1,000 items 13 containers 5 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Frederick Loewe was a German-born composer who wrote, with lyricist Alan Jay Lerner, the scores for such musicals as My Fair Lady, Camelot, Gigi, and Brigadoon. The collection contains music manuscripts from Loewe's stage and screen musicals, as well as individual songs not associated with a particular show. In addition, the collection contains photographs, a small amount of correspondence, clippings, business papers, writings, and programs.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Lerner, Alan Jay, 1918-1986.; Lerner, Alan Jay, 1918-1986.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988--Correspondence.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988--Manuscripts.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988--Photographs.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988. Brigadoon. Selections.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988. Camelot. Selections.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988. Gigi (Motion picture music). Selections.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988. Musicals. Selections.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988. My fair lady. Selections.; Loewe, Frederick, 1901-1988. Paint your wagon. Selections.
Organizations
Frederick Loewe Collection (Library of Congress)
Subjects
Composers.; Motion picture music--Scores.; Music--Manuscripts--United States.; Musical films.; Musical theater--United States--20th century.; Musicals--Scores.; Musicals.; Popular music--United States.; Theater--United States.
Form/Genre
Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
From 1962 to 1965, Frederick Loewe gave many of his most well-known music manuscripts to the Library of Congress. This gift was comprised of his manuscripts for songs from Brigadoon (given in 1962 ), songs from My Fair Lady (given in 1964 ), and songs written for Camelot, in addition to four additional songs written for My Fair Lady (given in 1965 ). These items were formerly cataloged as ML96.L62, though the contents were not fully described.
In November 1999, a significant collection of Frederick Loewe materials was offered at auction by Christie’s, Los Angeles. At that auction, the Library purchased five of the more important lots offered, with funds from the Ira and Leonore Gershwin Fund for the Benefit of the Library of Congress. Those lots contained additional songs written for Brigadoon, songs and sketches written for The Day Before Spring, songs and sketches written for Great Lady, songs written for, but not used in My Fair Lady, and songs written for Paint Your Wagon. The provenance of these materials was described in the catalog as a bequest from Loewe to “John Morris, artist and friend,” and a subsequent bequest by Morris to “the present owner” who is left unnamed. There were other lots offered for sale that the Library did not acquire, notably additional music written for Camelot, and music written for Gigi.
The remainder of the items in this collection were the gift of Stuart Warren of Palm Springs, California, and were received by the Library in December 1999. All non-music materials in the collection are also part of this gift.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Audiovisual materials were transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. An inventory of this material is available in the Music Division's collection file. Some of the audio recordings have been cataloged and can be found in the Library of Congress online catalog where they are identified as part of the "Frederick Loewe Collection (Library of Congress)."
Related Material
The Library of Congress Music Division holds additional Loewe material. The division’s general collections contain the following items: a typescript libretto for Great Lady (ML50.L8256G6), full scores for Brigadoon and My Fair Lady, and parts for My Fair Lady and Paint Your Wagon. In addition, the Warner-Chappell Collection contains parts and full scores for My Fair Lady, full scores for Paint Your Wagon, and piano-vocal scores for Camelot and Gigi. Robert Russell Bennett’s arrangement of themes from Camelot resides with the Robert Russell Bennett materials (ML96.B4673).
Access and Restrictions
The Frederick Loewe Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1901, June 10 Born, Berlin, Germany, to Edmund Loewe, a well-known Viennese tenor who originated the role of Prince Danilo in The Merry Widow ( 1906 ) and Rosa (Rose) Stagl Loewe, an actress. Loewe occasionally claimed that he was born in Vienna, Austria, which could have been due to his fear of anti-German sentiment after World War II
1906 Began piano lessons
1906-1914 Attended Berlin Military Academy
circa 1908 Began composing Contributed several numbers to his father's variety act
circa 1910-circa 1920 Studied music at Stern Conservatory in Berlin Studied piano with Ferruccio Busoni and Eugen d'Albert Studied composition and orchestrations with Emil Nikolaus von Rezniček
1914 Became the youngest piano soloist to appear with the Berlin Symphony Orchestra
1916 Composed hit song "Katrina"
1923 Awarded the Hollander Medal for piano
1924 Accompanied parents on a trip to the United States Gave a concert at New York’s Town Hall
circa 1925-circa 1929 Worked odd jobs in New York such as, busboy in a cafeteria, bantam weight boxer at a Brooklyn athletic club
circa 1929-circa 1930 Worked out West as itinerant cowboy, gold prospector, cowpuncher in Montana, mail carrier on horseback
circa 1930-circa 1939 Played piano in Greenwich Village nightclub and at the Rivoli Theatre, a movie house on Broadway; taught horseback riding at a New Hampshire resort; played piano on cruise ships and in Yorkville beerhalls
1931 Married Ernestine “Tina” Zwerleine, manager of the Hattie Carnegie fashion enterprises (divorced 1957)
1933 Played piano in pit orchestra for operetta Champagne, Sec Befriended cast member Kitty Carlisle
1935, Mar. 4 Operetta Petticoat Fever opened (Loewe song interpolated into its score)
1935 Joined the Lambs Club in New York
1935-1940 Worked on two unproduced musicals: Saints and Sinners in collaboration with Harold Rome, and The Milkman’s Serenade in collaboration with James Tranter
1936, Jan. 22 The Illustrator’s Show opened (Loewe song interpolated into its score)
1937, June 12 Salute to Spring, with Loewe score, opened in St. Louis, Missouri
1938, Dec. 1 Great Lady, with Loewe score, opened
1942, Mar. 27 Gave recital at Carnegie Chamber Music Hall, including excerpts from his own Insect Suite
1942 Met Alan Jay Lerner at the Lambs Club Lerner and Loewe composed the score for the show The Life of the Party
1943, Nov. 11 What’s Up?, with Lerner and Loewe score, opened
1945, Nov. 22 The Day Before Spring, with Lerner and Loewe score, opened
1947, Mar. 13 Brigadoon, with Lerner and Loewe score, opened
1951, Nov. 12 Paint Your Wagon, with Lerner and Loewe score, opened
1956, Mar. 15 My Fair Lady, with Lerner and Loewe score, opened
1958, Feb. 26 Suffered heart attack
1958 Gigi (film), with Lerner and Loewe score, released
1960, Dec. 3 Camelot, with Lerner and Loewe score, opened
1960-1969 Lived in Palm Springs, California in the winter, the Riviera in the spring, the Tyrol in the summer, and occasionally in New York
1962 Travelled to Japan with Burgess Meredith to research a musical
1967, Oct. 24 Doctor of Fine Arts (honorary degree), New York University
1973, Nov. 13 Stage version of Gigi opened, with four new Lerner and Loewe songs
1974 The Little Prince (film), with Lerner and Loewe score, released
1979, May 14 Gala tribute for Lerner and Loewe at the Winter Garden Theater
1985 Received Kennedy Center Honor
1986, June 14 Alan Jay Lerner died
1988, Feb. 14 Loewe died from a heart attack at his home, Palm Springs, California
Scope and Content Note
The Frederick Loewe Collection spans 1923-1988, with the bulk of the materials dating between 1945-1975. The Music series contains manuscripts from Loewe's stage and screen musicals, including songs cut from shows. It also contains individual songs not associated with a particular show and songs from less well-known shows. Of particular interest are autograph manuscripts from Loewe's most famous musicals, Brigadoon, Camelot, Gigi, My Fair Lady and Paint Your Wagon. The Miscellaneous Personal Papers series includes correspondence, various writings, programs, and clippings. The Photographs series contains over 500 photographs of Frederick Loewe, his family, friends, and home. The Business Papers series includes manuscript appraisals, records of charitable giving, and correspondence.
Organization of the Frederick Loewe Collection
The Frederick Loewe Collection is organized in four series:
Music
Miscellaneous Personal Papers
Photographs
Business Papers
http://lccn.loc.gov/2012563808
Container List
- Music (Box 1-9)
  - Show Music
    Arranged alphabetically by show title and by song title therein.
    - Brigadoon, 1947, Lyrics by Alan Jay Lerner (Box 1)
      - Almost like being in love
        - Piano-vocal score; 8 p. (Box-folder 1/1)
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 1/2)
      - Ballad of Jamie MacLean
        - Lead sheet; [1] p., No lyric; not used; Crossed out unidentified sketch on verso (Box-folder 1/3)
      - Brigadoon
        - Piano-vocal score; [2] p. (Box-folder 1/4)
        - Piano-choral score; 2 p. (Box-folder 1/4)
      - The chase
        - Piano-vocal score; p. 1-4, 6-10, 10A, 11 (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Come to me-bend to me
        - Piano-vocal score; 2 p. (Box-folder 1/6)
      - Come to me-bend to me ballet
        - Piano score; 6 p. (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Dancin' day
        - Lead sheet; [1] p., No lyric; not used (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Down on MacConnachy square
        - Piano-vocal score; [7] p. (Box-folder 1/9)
        - Choral arrangement; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Duty of a woman see Sketches
      - End of Lundie scene
        - Piano score; [1] p., Transition (Box-folder 1/10)
        - Choral sketch; [1] p., Vocal backstage intro (Box-folder 1/10)
        - Short score/sketch; 2 p. (Box-folder 1/10)
        - Choral score; [1] p., On verso of p. 2 of item above (Box-folder 1/10)
        - Copyist's manuscript piano-choral score; 2 p., Annotations in pencil (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Finale I
        - Piano-vocal score; 2 p., Not used; Leads into "Almost like being in love" (Box-folder 1/12)
      - From this day on
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 1/13)
        - Piano-vocal score; 1 p., Not used; with introduction/verse (Box-folder 1/13)
      - Gavotte
        - Piano score; 4 p., Not used (Box-folder 1/14)
      - Have a morning see Sketches
      - The heather on the hill
        - Piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 1/15)
        - 2 piano-vocal scores; 5 p. (Box-folder 1/16)
      - I insist see Sketches
      - I'll go home with Bonnie Jean
        - Piano-vocal score; 3 p., Crossed out lead sheet on verso of p. 1; Choral arrangement on verso of p. 2 (Box-folder 1/17)
        - Vocal arrangement sketch; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/17)
      - I'll go home with Bonnie Jean ballet
        - Piano score; 7 p., Crossed out sketch for "Almost like being in love" on verso of p. 1; Crossed out sketch for "Lundi chorale" on verso of p. 7 (Box-folder 1/18)
      - Jeannie's packin' up
        - Piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 1/19)
      - Jeannie's wedding day
        - Lead sheet; [1] p., No lyric; not used (Box-folder 1/20)
      - The love of my life
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 1/21)
      - The miracle
        - Piano score; [1] p., Not used; Crossed out 3 measure sketch on verso (Box-folder 1/22)
      - My mother's weddin' day
        - Piano-vocal score; 3 p. (Box-folder 1/23)
        - Piano-vocal score; [1] p., No lyric; On verso sketch labeled “Change de Mille–ballet” is a segment from “I’ll go home with Bonnie Jean ballet” (Box-folder 1/23)
      - Nothin' like a man
        - Piano-vocal score; 3 p., Not used; Crossed out sketch for “Jeannie’s wedding day” on verso of p. 1 and “The heather on the hill” on the verso of p. 3 (Box-folder 1/24)
      - Prologue
        - Piano-choral score; 2 p., Crossed out sketch on verso of p. 2 (Box-folder 1/25)
        - Piano-vocal score; [1] p., Mixed voices (Box-folder 1/25)
      - She doesn't hear me see also Sketches
        - Lead sheet; [1] p., No lyric; not used (Box-folder 1/26)
      - Sword dance
        - Piano score/piano-vocal score; [9] p. (Box-folder 1/27)
        - Piano score; 4 p., The reel (Box-folder 1/27)
        - Copyist's manuscript piano score/piano-vocal score; 6 p. (Box-folder 1/28)
      - There but for you go I
        - Piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 1/29)
      - True love see Sketches
      - Vendors' calls
        - Piano-choral score; 5 p., No lyric (Box-folder 1/30)
      - Waitin' for my Dearie
        - Piano-vocal score; 4 p., Crossed out lead sheets on verso’s of each page: Brigadoon; The heather on the hill; Waitin’ for my Dearie; There but for you go I (Box-folder 1/31)
        - Piano-choral score; 4 p., Insert; crossed out unidentified sketch on verso of p. 3 (Box-folder 1/31)
        - Piano-vocal score; 2 p., Insert (Box-folder 1/31)
      - We're very lucky see Sketches
      - Wooin' in the highlands
        - Lead sheet; [1] p., No lyric; not used (Box-folder 1/32)
      - Sketches; [4] p., No lyric; Titles include: unidentified; True love; Heather; Waitin' for my dearie; She doesn't hear me; Duty of a woman (Box-folder 1/33)
      - Sketches; [7] p., No lyric; Titles include: Sword dance; Finale I; She doesn't hear me; There but for you go I; We're very lucky; The heather on the hill; I insist; Have a morning; I'll go home with Bonnie Jean; Prologue; unidentified (Box-folder 1/34)
      - Piano-vocal selections; [15] p., In Swedish (Box-folder 1/35)
      - Original manuscript folder, Laid in: song list (Box-folder 1/25)
    - Camelot, 1960, Lyrics by Alan Jay Lerner (Box 2)
      - Before I gaze at you again
        - Piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 2/1)
      - Camelot
        - Piano-vocal score; 9 p. (Box-folder 2/2)
        - Sheet music (Box-folder 2/19)
      - C'est moi
        - Piano-vocal score; 7 p. (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Finale ultimo
        - Piano-vocal score; 6 p. (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Follow me (Nimue's call)
        - Piano-vocal score; 3 p. (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Guenevere
        - Piano-vocal score; 16 p. (Box-folder 2/6)
      - How to handle a woman
        - Piano-vocal score; 7 p. (Box-folder 2/7)
        - Sheet music (Box-folder 2/19)
      - I loved you once in silence
        - Piano-vocal score; 6 p., Verse, based on “The simple joys of maidenhood,” crossed out (Box-folder 2/8)
      - I wonder what the king is doing tonight
        - Piano-vocal score; 8 p. (Box-folder 2/9)
      - If ever I would leave you
        - Piano-vocal score; 4 p., On verso of p. 2 crossed out sketches for “Sir Dinnerdan” and “King’s interlude”; On verso of p. 3 crossed out lead sheet for “Follow me (Nimue’s call)” (Box-folder 2/10)
        - Piano-vocal score; 3 p., Madrigal; not used; Note on p. 3: Att. Franz [Allers], I would prefer it if Goulet could do it in C–if not, transpose the Madrigal accordingly. Thanks F. (Box-folder 2/10)
        - Sheet music (Box-folder 2/19)
      - The jousts
        - Piano-vocal score; 16 p. (Box-folder 2/11)
      - The lusty month of May
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 2/12)
      - March
        - Piano score; 3 p. (Box-folder 2/13)
      - Overture
        - Piano score; 4 p., “Fanfare” on verso of p. 1 (Box-folder 2/14)
      - The persuasion
        - Piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 2/15)
      - The seven deadly virtues
        - Piano-vocal score; 6 p. (Box-folder 2/16)
      - The simple joys of maidenhood
        - Piano-vocal score; 10 p. (Box-folder 2/17)
        - Lead sheet; 2 p., Gershwin Fund Collection (Box-folder 2/17)
      - What do the simple folk do? see also Please don’t marry me from My Fair Lady
        - Piano-vocal score; 15 p. (Box-folder 2/18)
      - Vocal selections; 27 p. (Box-folder 2/19)
    - The day before spring, 1945, Lyrics by Alan Jay Lerner (Box 3)
      - Anyone else
        - Lead sheet; [1] p., Not used; Crossed out sketch for “For anyone else” on verso (Box-folder 3/1)
        - Lead sheet; [1] p., Verse: sketch for “Where’s my wife” on verso (Box-folder 3/1)
      - Ballet I (Eternal youth)
        - Lead sheet/condensed score; 3 p. (Box-folder 3/2)
        - Copyist's manuscript piano score/piano-choral score; 14 p., Includes song “You haven’t changed at all” (Box-folder 3/3)
      - Book ballet see Peter reads the book
      - Bridge
        - Copyist's manuscript piano score; 8 p. (Box-folder 3/4)
      - The day before spring
        - Piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 3/5)
        - Copyist's manuscript short score/piano-vocal score; 4 p., Includes introduction (Box-folder 3/5)
        - Copyist's manuscript piano-vocal score; 3 p. (Box-folder 3/5)
        - Copyist's manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p., In folder marked: Peter reads the book (from duet D.B.S.) (Box-folder 3/5)
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 3/6)
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 3/6)
      - Finale I
        - Copyist's manuscript piano-vocal score; 9 p., Incomplete (Box-folder 3/7)
      - Friends to the end
        - Lead sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 3/8)
      - For anyone else see Anyone else and My love is a married man
      - God's green world
        - Piano-vocal score; 9 p. (Box-folder 3/9)
        - Piano-vocal score; 9 p. (Box-folder 3/9)
      - I love you this morning
        - Piano-vocal score; 2 p., Incomplete (Box-folder 3/10)
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 3/11)
      - The invitation
        - Piano-vocal score; [9] p. (Box-folder 3/12)
      - A jug of wine
        - Copyist's manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p., Annotations; Pencil sketch on verso of cover page (Box-folder 3/13)
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 3/14)
      - Love bower see Where's my wife
      - My love is a married man
        - Lead sheet; [1] p., No lyric; On verso lead sheet in pencil, no lyric for “For anyone else" (Box-folder 3/15)
        - Piano-vocal score; 7 p. (Box-folder 3/16)
        - Piano-vocal score; 7 p. (Box-folder 3/16)
      - Peter reads the book
        - Piano-vocal score; 13 p., Crossed out music on verso of p. 11; Crossed out title “Book ballet” on p. 1 (Box-folder 3/17)
      - This is my holiday
        - Piano-vocal score; p. 4-8, Incomplete; most of p. 4 crossed out (Box-folder 3/18)
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 3/19)
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 3/19)
      - Where's my wife
        - Lead sheet; 4 p., No lyric (Box-folder 3/20)
        - Piano-vocal score; [15] p., Music reworked as verse for “Gigi”; Crossed out sketch for “The day before spring” on the verso of p. 1; Sketch for “Love bower” crossed out on the verso of p. 9; P. 6 was found with separate gift (Box-folder 3/20)
      - The woman who falls
        - Lead sheet; [1] p., No lyric; Sketch for “Jug of wine verse” on verso (Box-folder 3/21)
      - You haven't changed at all
        - Piano-vocal score;5 p., Crossed out sketch on verso of p. 4 (Box-folder 3/22)
        - Choral arrangement; 7 p., For ballet I (Box-folder 3/23)
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 3/24)
      - Miscellaneous music
        - Copyist's manuscript piano score; [1] p., Annotations; Titles include: Intr. Jug of wine; 1st ending Jug of wine; Intr. God’s green world; 2nd ending God’s green world; 1 m. pencil sketch on verso (Box-folder 3/25)
      - Song lists and title pages, 4 items (Box-folder 3/26)
      - Souvenir program, Printed with artist’s bios, production photos, synopsis and history of show (Box-folder 3/27)
    - Gigi, 1958 film, 1973 stage adaptation, Lyrics by Alan Jay Lerner (Box 3)
      - Gigi see also Where's my wife from The day before spring
        - Piano-vocal score; 7 p. (Box-folder 3/28)
      - I never want to go home again
        - Copyist's manuscript piano-vocal score; 9 p. (Box-folder 3/29)
      - I remember it well
        - Piano-vocal score; 7 p. (Box-folder 3/30)
      - I'm glad I'm not young anymore
        - Piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 3/31)
      - The night they invented champagne
        - Piano-vocal score; cover and p. 5 only (Box-folder 3/32)
      - Waltz at Maxim's (she is not thinking of me)
        - Piano score; 7 p., Annotations (Box-folder 3/33)
    - Great lady, 1938, Lyrics by Earl Crooker (Box 4)
      - And so will you
        - Copyist's manuscript piano part; [2] p., Annotations (Box-folder 4/1)
      - Ballad of the streetsinger
        - Copyist's manuscript piano-vocal score; 6 p., Annotations (Box-folder 4/2)
      - Change into past
        - Copyist's manuscript piano score; [1] p., Annotations (Box-folder 4/3)
      - Cinderella see Vocal selections
      - Goodnight madame see also Vocal selections
        - 2 copyist's manuscript piano-vocal scores; [3], 3 p., Annotations (Box-folder 4/4)
      - I can see myself in the theatre see Miscellaneous
      - I have room in my heart
        - Piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 4/5)
      - I'll take my love see also Vocal selections and Fragments
        - Copyist's manuscript piano-vocal score; [4] p., Annotations (Box-folder 4/6)
      - The little corporal see Vocal selections
      - Madame is at home see Vocal selections, Miscellaneous and Fragments
      - May I suggest
        - Copyist's manuscript piano part/short score; 5 p., Annotations (Box-folder 4/7)
      - The night can be blind see Vocal selections
      - One little pilgrim's progress (Silhouette ballet)
        - Piano-vocal score; 7 p. (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Once in every lifetime see Vocal selections
      - Promenade see also Vocal selections
        - Copyist's manuscript piano-vocal score; 6 p., Annotations (Box-folder 4/9)
      - Road to Paris see Vocal selections
      - There had to be a waltz see Vocal selections
      - To whom it may concern see Vocal selections
      - Tongues may wag see also Vocal selections
        - 2 copyist's manuscript piano-vocal scores; 7 p., One with annotations (Box-folder 4/10)
      - Transition Act I and Transition Act II see Vocal selections
      - Transition scene 6
        - Copyist's manuscript piano part; 15 p., Annotations; Sketch on cover page (Box-folder 4/11)
      - Transition scene 6-7 Act I see Miscellaneous
      - Transition to "Just a stitch in time"
        - Piano score; [1] p., Incomplete (Box-folder 4/12)
      - Why can't this night last forever see Vocal selections
      - Vocal selections
        - Lead sheets; [38] p., Titles include: I'll take my love; Promenade; Goodnight madame; Why can't this night last forever; Cinderella; Once in every lifetime; Madame is at home; Road to Paris; Tongues may wag; Transaction act I; Transition act II; The night can be blind; Linkmen; Officers (Box-folder 4/13)
        - Lead sheets; [5] p., Titles include: There had to be a waltz; The little corporal (Box-folder 4/14)
      - Miscellaneous